now let's investigate what it means to
negate a conditional so in this case I I
have this conditional P implies q and
then the question is what happens if I'm
going to negate that particular
conditional now what I'm going to do is
I'm going to use just a bunch of logical
equivalences here I'm going to get some
result and then we're going to see
whether that result makes sense to us so
the first thing that I can say is that
we know that that I can take this P
implies q and we've just shown that this
is logically equivalent to I'm not
changing the not here at all but we know
that the inside the conditional is
logically equivalent to not P or
Q so that was one step and now I have a
disjunctive an or statement in the
center and then a knot in front of it
and we know that one of De Morgan's laws
applies for a scenario like this that I
can take the knot and I can distribute
it through but it does two things it
takes the or to an and and it takes a
knot in front of both of the two
different sides so in other words I'm
going to claim that this is logically
equivalent to the first thing is I'm
going to bring the not to the inside so
it goes not not
p and then it flips the or to an and so
I go to an and and then I take the KN
and I put it in front of the Q as well
and so I go not q and this was demorgan
and then I also note that here I have
this this double negative and we
previously seen that I can manipulate
the double negatives not not p is the
same thing logically as just P so I can
say that this is the first thing and not
Q now this should make some sense to us
if we think about what an implication
was there was only going to be one way
that the implication
was not going to be true when the
Assumption the hypothesis was true but
that the conclusion was going to be
false that was the only one in our truth
table that gave a value of false for the
implication and that's what we have here
the first one has to be true the
Assumption and it has to be the case
that the conclusion needs to be false
that was the one scenario the other
scenarios like for example when P was
false those were lumped into the vacuous
L true scenario and of course when P was
true and Q was true that was also going
to be true for the implication as well
so what we managed to prove here by
showing a bunch of logical equivalences
is the result that is the exact same
result we would have gotten if we just
gone to the truth table and negated the
column for p implies Q so we've got the
same result which is good